# **Dingzhong Zhang**

### Mechanical Engineer

Montréal, Québec +1 438 941 0215 dingzhong.zhang@mail.mcgill.ca Dzzhang96.github.io

#### **Profile**

Mechanical Engineer with expertise in surgical navigation, medical image processing and robotics. Specializing in the design, implementation, and testing of biomedical devices and robotic systems. Capable of enhancing software through implementing deep learning and algorithm optimization.

#### Work Experience

#### **Algorithm Development Intern**

June 2021 - Aug 2021

Medtronic: MTC - Visualization | Robotics Team

- Distortion correction and calibration of intra-operative spine X-ray images using DLT algorithm.
- 2D-3D image registration between X-ray and DRR images for C-Arm image-assisted surgical navigation system.
- Implemented an iterative U-net for automatic vertebra segmentation, including the first and last partially visible vertebrae.

#### **Robotics Engineer Intern**

June 2020 – Aug 2020

Shanghai Genius Education & Technology Co. Ltd (UBTECH Robotics): Shanghai, China

- Designed and assembled first-person-view drones and applied control theory to improve flight stability.
- Developed a line-following-vehicle project for students to gain hands-on experience with MircroBit and Python.
- Taught classes of up to 15 students in flight regulation, python programming, and using Arduino hardware.

Research Assistant Dec 2018 – July 2019

Orthotek Laboratory: Shanghai, China

- Established a universal test platform for replicating different movement/load scenarios for prosthetic knee joints.
- Simulated and analysed loading conditions with kinematics tests using an ABB IRB6700 robotic arm.
- Improved-prosthesis control methods by analysing load conditions using a multidimensional force sensor, Beckhoff embedded PC, and secondary developed software based on TwinCat.
- Developed a dynamic optical measuring system to observe knee-joint kinematics in gait by sticking markers on the surface of prosthesis.

#### Academic Research

# Augmented Reality based Spine Surgical Navigation System using Polaris & HoloLens

Sept 2020 - Present

McGill University

- Developed an AR based surgical navigation software for high-quality visualization during spine surgery.
- Proposed a quick and accurate workflow for calibration of surgical instruments and registration of models.
- Segmented the vertebra automatically from DICOM using an iterative U-net neural network and designed experiments to evaluate the accuracy by using FaroArm coordinate measurement.

#### **Orbital Rim Registration Software**

Jan 2020 – June 2020

Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital

- Developed a software in QT using C++ that allows doctors to register points along different orbital rims for ocular surgery procedures.
- Applied the iterative-closest-point algorithm for surface registration in drafted 3D models from CT-scan data.

## **Medical Image Segmentation via Deep Learning**

Sept 2019 - Nov 2019

Shanghai Jiao Tong University

- Reduced calculation time by 80% for a medical image computation software by integrating deep learning.
- Compiled the TensorFlow C++ library and converted Python image segmentation programs to C++.
- Developed semi-automatic labelling algorithms to segment the bone graft from maxillary sinus for training models.

#### **Design of a Medical Rehabilitation Robotic Arm**

Jan 2018 - Jun 2018

Shanghai University

- Earned First Prize in the Chinese Service Robot Competition.
- Prototyped a robotic arm with four degrees of freedom which can predict patient arm movement to aid in rehabilitation exercises and adjust its sensitivity for different patients.
- Developed a robotic arm system equipped with multiple sensors, a windows forms application, and servo controls.
- Conducted force analysis in ANSYS to increase stiffness and strength as needed for various situations.

Shanghai University

- Developed a first-person-view drone to win First Prize in China's Aerial Robotics Competition.
- Built a drone with 4x 4800kv brushless motors, carbon fibre frame, 4 in 1 electronic speed controller, F3 flight controller, altimeter, barometer, video transmitter, etc.
- Actively calibrated the drone's PID to adjust for various match requirements and conditions.

# Programming and Design of a PCB Layout of an Automated Guided Vehicle

Nov 2017 - Mar 2018

Shanghai University

- Won Third Prize in China's Robot Match for Travel and Security.
- Programmed a vehicle to pass different terrains and execute corresponding actions after scanning QR codes.
- Improved system reliability by designing an expansion PCB to replace multiple parts connected with Dupont cables.
- Optimized vehicle response by installing an automatic steering system featuring 16 gray-scale sensors, 4 ultrasonic sensors and a control algorithm.

## **Publications**

#### **Reviewing:**

• Yuwei Gu, **Dingzhong Zhang**, Baoxin Tao, Feng Wang, Xiaojun Chen, Yiqun Wu. (2021). A novel technique to quantify radiographic bone-to-implant contact of zygomatic implants based on three-dimensional image registration and segmentation. Dentomaxillofacial Radiology.

#### **Published (Selected):**

- Haitao Li<sup>#</sup>, Jiangchang Xu<sup>#</sup>, **Dingzhong Zhang**, Yaohua He, Xiaojun Chen\*. (2022). An Automatic Surgical Planning Combining Bone Density Assessment and Path Integral in Cone Area for Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty. International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery.
- Jiangchang Xu<sup>#</sup>, Jiannan Liu<sup>#</sup>, **Dingzhong Zhang**, Zijie Zhou, Chenping Zhang, Xiaojun Chen\*. (2021). A 3D Segmentation Network of Mandible from CT Scan with Combination of Multiple Convolutional Modules and Edge Supervision in Mandibular Reconstruction. Computers in Biology and Medicine.
- Jiangchang Xu<sup>#</sup>, Jiannan Liu<sup>#</sup>, **Dingzhong Zhang**, Zijie Zhou, Xiaoyi Jiang, Chenping Zhang, Xiaojun Chen\*. (2021). Automatic Mandible Segmentation from CT Image Using 3D Fully Convolutional Neural Network Based on DenseASPP and Attention Gates. International Journal of Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery.

#### Education

McGill University

Sept 2020 – Present

Master of Science – Mechanical Engineering (GPA: 4.00 / 4.00)

Shanghai Jiao Tong University

Sept 2019 -Sept 2021

• Master of Science – Mechanical Engineering (GPA: 3.64 / 4.00)

Shanghai University

Sept 2014 - June 2019

• Bachelors of Engineering – Mechanical Engineering (GPA: 3.72 / 4.00 RANK: 1/277)

#### **Core Competencies**

Specialization	Technical Skills			Soft Skills
<ul> <li>AR/VR Navigation</li> </ul>	<ul><li>ANSYS</li></ul>	<ul><li>OpenCV</li></ul>	• ROS	<ul><li>Adaptable</li></ul>
<ul> <li>Medical Image Processing</li> </ul>	<ul><li>AutoCAD</li></ul>	<ul><li>Python</li></ul>	<ul> <li>Solidworks</li> </ul>	<ul><li>Analytical</li></ul>
<ul> <li>Robotics</li> </ul>	• C++	<ul><li>PyTorch</li></ul>	<ul><li>Visual Studio</li></ul>	<ul> <li>Communication</li> </ul>
<ul><li>Programming</li></ul>	<ul><li>MATLAB</li></ul>	• Qt	<ul><li>VTK, ITK</li></ul>	<ul> <li>Optimization Oriented</li> </ul>

#### **Awards & Honors**

Grad Excellence Award - McGill University	2021
Academic Excellence Scholarship - Shanghai Jiao Tong University	2019
Graduated with Honors of Shanghai	2019
Academic Scholarship - Shanghai University	2015 - 2018
• First Prize - Chinese Service Robot Competition (Innovative Design of Rehabilitation Robot)	2018
First Prize - China Aerial Robotics Competition	2018
• Third Prize - China Robot Match (Travel and Security)	2018

# Languages

• English (Fluent) • French (B1) • Chinese (Fluent)